So, last month, the Encyclopaedia Britannica announced
الشهر الماضي ، أعلنت موسوعة بريتانيكا
that it is going out of print
أنها ستتوقف عن الطباعة
after 244 years, which made me nostalgic,
بعد 244 عاماً ، مما جعلني أشعر بالحنين
because I remember playing a game with the colossal encyclopedia set in my hometown library
لأنني أتذكر اللعب بالطاقم الهائل للموسوعة في مكتبة مدينتي
back when I was a kid,
عندما كنت طفلاً
maybe 12 years old.
احتمال عند الثانية عشر من عمري
And I wondered if I could update that game,
وتسائلت هل أستطيع تحديث هذه اللعبة
not just for modern methods,
ليس فقط بالطرق الحديثة
but for the modern me.
ولكن بتحديثي شخصياَ
So I tried.
لذلك فقد حاولت
I went to an online encyclopedia,
دخلت على موسوعة على الانترنت
Wikipedia, and I entered the term "Earth."
ويكبيديا، وأدخلت مصطلح "أرض"
You can start anywhere, this time I chose Earth.
يمكنك البدء من أي مكان، هذه المرة اخترت الأرض
And the first rule of the game is pretty simple.
وأول قواعد اللعبة سهلاً نوعاً ما
You just have to read the article
ما عليك سوى قراءة المقالة
until you find something you don't know,
حتى تجد شيئاَ لا تعلمه
and preferably something your dad doesn't even know.
ومن المستحسن ألا يعلم حتى أباك عنه
And in this case, I quickly found this:
وفي هذه الحالة ، بسرعة وجدت هذا :
The furthest point from the center of the Earth
لم تكن أبعد نقطة من مركز الأرض
is not the tip of Mount Everest, like I might have thought,
هي قمة جبل افرست ، كما كنت أعتقد
it's the tip of this mountain: Mount Chimborazo in Ecuador.
إنها قمة هذا الجبل ، جبل شيمبورازو في الإكوادور
The Earth spins, of course, as it travels around the sun,
تدور الأرض بالطبع في رحلتها حول الشمس
so the Earth bulges a little bit around the middle,
لذا فإن الأرض تنتفخ قليلاً حول الوسط
like some Earthlings.
مثل بعض الناس
And even though Mount Chimborazo isn't the tallest mountain in the Andes,
وبالرغم من أن جبل شيمبرازو ليس أطول جبل في الإنديز
it's one degree away from the equator,
فهو يبعد درجة واحدة عن خط الإستواء
it's riding that bulge, and so the summit of Chimborazo
فهو يمتطي هذا الانتفاخ وكذلك مؤتمر شيمبرازو
is the farthest point on Earth from the center of the Earth.
هو أبعد نقطة على الأرض من مركز الأرض
And it is really fun to say.
ومن الممتع بالفعل قول ذلك
So I immediately decided,
وعلى الفور فقد قررت
this is going to be the name of the game,
أن يصبح هذا إسم اللعبة
or my new exclamation.
أو علامة التعجب خاصتي
You can use it at TED.
يمكنكم استخدامها في TED
Chimborazo, right?
شيمبرازو ، صحيح؟
It's like "eureka" and "bingo" had a baby.
أنها مثل حصول "إيوريكا" و"بينجو" على طفل
I didn't know that;
لم أكن أعلم ذلك
that's pretty cool.
هذا جيد بالفعل
Chimborazo!
شيمبرازو
So the next rule of the game is also pretty simple.
ولذا فإن القاعدة التالية من اللعبة سهلة كذلك
You just have to find another term and look that up.
ما عليك سوى ايجاد مصطلح آخر والبحث عنه
Now in the old days, that meant getting out a volume
في الأيام الخوالي ، ذلك يعني الحصول على مجلد آخر
and browsing through it alphabetically,
وتصفحه أبجدياً
maybe getting sidetracked,
يمكن أن تجده في الهوامش
that was fun.
كان هذا ممتعاً
Nowadays there are hundreds of links to choose from.
حالياً يوجد المئات من الروابط لتختار منها
I can go literally anywhere in the world,
يمكنني أن أذهب حرفياً إلى أي مكان في العالم
I think since I was already in Ecuador,
أعتقد بما أنني كنت بالفعل في الإكوادور
I just decided to click on the word "tropical."
فقد قررت الضغط على كلمة " أستوائي"
That took me to this wet and warm band of the tropics
وأخذني ذلك لهذا الحزام الاستوائي الرطب والدافيء
that encircles the Earth.
الذي يحيط بالأرض
Now that's the Tropic of Cancer in the north
الآن هذا هو مدار السرطان في الشمال
and the Tropic of Capricorn in the south,
وهذا مدار العقرب في الجنوب
that much I knew,
الذي أعرفه كثيراً
but I was surprised to learn this little fact:
ولكني اندهشت عندما علمت هذه الحقيقة الصغيرة
Those are not cartographers' lines,
لم يكن هؤلاء خطوطاً مرسومة بواسطة رسامي الخرائط
like latitude or the borders between nations,
مثل خط العرض أو الحدود بين الدول
they are astronomical phenomena caused by the Earth's tilt,
إنها ظواهر فلكية تكونت بسبب ميل الأرض
and they change.
وهي تتغير
They move; they go up, they go down.
تتحرك ، تذهب للأعلى وتعود للأسفل
In fact, for years, the Tropic of Cancer and the Tropic of Capricorn
في الواقع ، لأعوام، انجرف
have been steadily drifting towards the equator
مدار السرطان ومدار العقرب بثبات نحو خط الاستواء
at the rate of about 15 meters per year,
بمعدل يصل الى 15 متر كل عام
and nobody told me that.
ولم يخبرني أحد بذلك
I didn't know it.
لم أكن أعلمه
Chimborazo!
شيمبرازو
So to keep the game going, I just have to find another term and look that one up.
وللحفاظ على استمرار اللعبة ، كان علي ايجاد مصطلح آخر والبحث عنه
Since I'm already in the tropics, I chose "Tropical rainforest."
وبما أنني في الاستوائيات ، أختار " الغابات الاستوائية"
Famous for its diversity, human diversity.
المشهورة بتنوعها وتنوع ساكنيها من البشر
There are still dozens and dozens of uncontacted tribes living on this planet.
ما زال هناك العديد والعديد من القبائل المنعزلة تعيش على هذا الكوكب
They're all over the globe, but virtually all of them live in tropical rainforests.
انهم ينتشرون على الكرة الأرضية ولكنهم عملياً يعيشون في الغابات الاستوائية
This is the only place you can go nowadays and not get "friended."
هذا هو المكان الوحيد الذي تستطيع الذهاب إليه في أيامنا هذه ولا يرحب بك
The link that I clicked on here was exotic in the beginning and then absolutely mysterious at the very end.
كان الرابط الذي ضغطت عليه هنا مثيراً في البداية ومن ثم اصبح غامضاً جداً في النهاية
It mentioned leopards and ring-tailed coatis and poison dart frogs and boa constrictors and then
ذكر النمر المنقط و الراكون ذو الذيل الدائري والضفادع السامة وأفعى البوا ومن ثم
coleoptera,
الجعلان الاستوائية
which turn out to be beetles.
والتي تتحول إلى خنافس
Now I clicked on this on purpose,
والأن ضغطت على هذا لغرض ما
but if I'd somehow gotten here by mistake,
ولكنني وصلت الى هنا عن طريق الخطأ
it does remind me, for the band, see "The Beatles,"
لقد ذكرتني بالفرقة الموسيقية انظر "الخنافس"
for the car see "Volkswagon Beetle,"
وللسيارة انظر "خنفسة الفولكس فاجن"
but I am here for beetle beetles.
ولكنني هنا من أجل خنفسة الخنافس
This is the most successful order on the planet by far.
هذا أكثر نظام ناجح على الكوكب حتى الآن
Something between 20 and 25 percent of all life forms on the planet,
شيئ بين 20 و ال 25 بالمائة من كل أشكال الحياة على الكوكب
including plants, are beetles.
بما فيها النباتات ، هي الخنافس
That means the next time you are in the grocery store,
هذا يعني انك عندما تكون المرة القادمة في محل البقالة
take a look at the four people ahead of you in line.
اأنظر إلى الأربعة أشخاص أمامك في الصف
Statistically, one of you is a beetle.
احصائياً ، واحد منكم هو خنفسة
And if it is you, you are astonishingly well adapted.
ولو كنت انت كذلك ، فإنك متأقلم بصورة مدهشة
There are scavenger beetles that pick the skin and flesh off of bones in museums.
هناك الخنافس نابشة القمامة التي تلتقط الجلد واللحم وتنزعه عن العظام في المتاحف
There are predator beetles, that attack other insects
إنها خنافس آكلة اللحوم ، التي تهاجم الحشرات الأخرى
and still look pretty cute to us.
ولا تزال تحتفظ بشكلها الجميل لنا
There are beetles that roll little balls of dung
هناك الخنافس التي تدحرج كرات صغيرة من الروث
great distances across the desert floor to feed to their hatchlings.
لمسافات بعيدة عبر أرض الصحراء لتطعم صغارها
This reminded the ancient Egyptians of their god Khepri,
هذا يذكرنا بالقدماء المصريين و بمعبودهم خبري
who renews the ball of the sun every morning,
الذي يجدد كرة الشمس كل صباح
which is how that dung-rolling scarab
مثل الجعران الذي يدحرج الروث
became that sacred scarab on the breastplate of the Pharaoh Tutankhamun.
أصبح الجعران الخائف على لوحة صدر الفرعون توت عنخ آمون
Beetles, I was reminded, have the most romantic flirtation in the animal kingdom.
الخنافس ، لقد تذكرت ، لديها أكثر المداعبات الرومانسية في مملكة الحيوان
Fireflies are not flies, fireflies are beetles.
اليرعات لا تستطيع الطيران ، اليرعات في الحقيقة خنافس
Fireflies are coleoptera, and coleoptera communicate in other ways as well.
اليرعات هي جعالين والجعالين تتواصل بطرق أخرى
Like my next link:
مثل رابطي التالي
The chemical language of pheromones.
اللغة الكيميائية للفيرمونات
Now the pheromone page took me to a video of a sea urchin having sex.
والآن أخذتني صفحة الفيرمونات إلى فيديو لقنفذ البحر يمارس الجنس
Yeah.
نعم
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And the link to aphrodisiac.
ورابط المنشط الجنسي
Now that's something that increases sexual desire,
وهو شيئ يزيد من الرغبة الجنسية
possibly chocolate.
من الممكن أن يكون شوكولاتة
There is a compound in chocolate called phenethylamine
يوجد مكون في الشوكولاتة يسمى فينيثيلامين
that might be an aphrodisiac.
من المحتمل أن يكون منشطاً جنسياً
But as the article mentions,
ولكن كما ذكرت المقالة
because of enzyme breakdown,
وبسبب تقسيم الانزيمات
it's unlikely that phenethylamine will reach your brain if taken orally.
فإنه على العكس لو أخذ بالفم سيصل الفينثيلامين إلى مخك
So those of you who only eat your chocolate, you might have to experiment.
لذا من منكم الذي يأكلون الشوكولاتة فقط ، يمكنكم تجربته
The link I clicked on here,
الرابط الذي ضغطته هنا
"sympathetic magic," mostly because I understand what both of those words mean.
"السحر العاطفي" ، غالباً لأنني أفهم ماتعنيه هاتان الكلمتان
But not when they're together like that.
ولكن ليس وهما مرتبطتان كذلك
I do like sympathy. I do like magic.
إني أحب العاطفة ، وأحب السحر
So when I click on "sympathetic magic,"
لذا عندما أضغط على "السحر العاطفي"
I get sympathetic magic and voodoo dolls.
أحصل على السحر العاطفي ودميات المشعوذين
This is the boy in me getting lucky again.
أنه الصبي داخلي الذي يحالفه الحظ مرة ثانية
Sympathetic magic is imitation.
السحر العاطفي تقليد
If you imitate something, maybe you can have an effect on it.
لو قلدت شيئاً ، من المحتمل أن تؤثر فيه
That's the idea behind voodoo dolls, and possibly also cave paintings.
هذه هي الفكرة عن دميات المشعوذين ، واحتمال رسومات الكهوف كذلك
The link to cave paintings takes me to some of the oldest art known to humankind.
يأخذني رابط رسومات الكهوف إلى بعض من الفنون المعروف للجنس البشري
I would love to see Google maps inside some of these caves.
أود أن أرى خرائط جوجل داخل بعض من هذه الكهوف
We've got tens-of-thousands-years-old artwork.
حصلنا على عمل فني عمره عشرات الآلاف من الأعوام
Common themes around the globe include large wild animals and tracings of human hands,
المواضيع المشتركة في جميع أنحاء العالم تشمل الحيوانات البرية الكبيرة واقتفاء أثر من يد الإنسان،
usually the left hand.
عادة اليد اليسرى
We have been a dominantly right-handed tribe for millenia,
لقد كنا قبيلة تهيمن عليها اليد اليمنى لقرون
so even though I don't know why a paleolithic person would trace his hand
وبالرغم من ذلك لا أعرف لماذا يقتفي انسان العصر الحجري آثار يده
or blow pigment on it from a tube,
أو ينفخ الألوان عليها من أنبوب
I can easily picture how he did it.
يمكنني بسهولة تصوير كيف فعلها
And I really don't think it's that different form our own little dominant hand avatar
وأنا حقاً لا أعتقد أن هذا الشكل المختلف ل ليدنا المهيمنة
right there that I'm going to use now to click on the term for "hand,"
هناك فقط ، سأقوم بالضغط على مصطلح "يد"
go to the page for "hand," where I found the most fun and possibly embarrassing bit of trivia
ذهبت الى صفحة "يد" حيث وجدت أكثر المعلومات الصغيرة الممتعة والمحرجة
I've found in a long time. It's simply this:
التي وجدتها منذ وقت طويل. هي ببساطة هذه:
The back of the hand is formally called the opisthenar.
ظهر اليد يدعى رسمياً اوبيسثينار
Now that's embarrassing, because up until now,
والآن هذا محرج ، لانه حتى الآن
every time I've said, "I know it like the back of my hand,"
وفي كل مرة أقول "أعرفه مثل ظهر يدي"
I've really been saying, "I'm totally familiar with that,
أنا بالفعل أقول ذلك ، "انا معتاد تماماً على ذلك ،
I just don't know it's freaking name, right?"
أنا فقط لا أعرف هذا الإسم المخيف ، أليس كذلك؟ "
And the link I clicked on here,
والرابط الذي ضغطته هنا
well, lemurs, monkeys and chimpanzees have the little opisthenar.
حسناً ، الليمور ، والقرود والشيمبانزي لها الأوبيسثينار الصغير
I click on chimpanzee, and I get our closest genetic relative.
أضغط على رابط الشيمبانزي وأتوصل إلى القريب الأقرب جينياً لنا
Pan troglodytes, the name we give him, means "cave dweller."
بان تروجلودايتس ، الأسم الذي اطلقناه عليه ، يعني ساكن الكهف
He doesn't.
وهو ليس كذلك
He lives in rainforests and savannas.
فهو يعيش في الغابات المطيرة و السافانا
It's just that we're always thinking of this guy as lagging behind us,
هذا هو بالضبط ما اعتقدناه دائماً عن هذا الكائن المتخلف
evolutionarily or somehow uncannily creeping up on us,
بطريقة تطورية أو خارقة للطبيعة يزحف نحونا
and in some cases, he gets places before us.
وفي بعض الحالات يحصل على الأماكن قبلنا
Like my next link, the almost irresistible link, Ham the Astrochimp.
مثل رابطي التالي ، أكثر الروابط التي لا تقاوم ، رائد الفضاء الشامبانزي هام
I click on him, and I really thought he was going to bring me full circle twice, in fact.
ضغطته ، اعتقدت في الحقيقة أنه سوف يمنحني دائرة كاملة مرتين ، في الواقع
He's born in Cameroon,
هو قد ولد في الكاميرون
which is smack in the middle of my tropics map,
والتي تقع في وسط خريطتي الاستوائية
and more specifically his skeleton wound up in the Smithsonian museum getting picked clean by beetles.
وقد كانت نهاية هيلكه العظمي على وجه التحديد في متحف سميثسونيان بعد ان تم تنظيفه بواسطة الخنافس
In between those two landmarks in Ham's life,
في الوسط من هاتين النقطتين من حياة هام
he flew into space.
فقد طار في الفضاء
He experienced weightlessness and re-entry
وجرب انعدام الوزن والخروج والعودة
months before the first human being to do it,
بشهور قبل أن يفعل الإنسان ذلك ،
Soviet cosmonaut Yuri Gagarin.
رائد الفضاء السوفيتي يوري جاجا رين
When I click on Yuri Gagarin's page,
وعندما ضغطت على صفحة يوري جاجارين
I get this guy who was surprisingly short in stature,
وجدت هذا الرجل الذي كان قصير القامة بطريقة مدهشة
huge in heroism.
ضخم في البطولة.
Top estimates, Soviet estimates, put this guy at 1.65 meters,
أعلى التقديرات ، التقديرات السوفيتية ، وضعت هذا الرجل على 1.65 متر
that is less than five and a half feet tall max,
وهذا يقل عن خمسة ونصف قدم طول ،
possibly because he was malnourished as a child.
احتمال لأنه كان يعاني من سوء التغذية وهو طفل
Germans occupied Russia.
احتل الألمان روسيا
A Nazi officer took over the Gagarin household,
وأخذ مكتب النازي بيت جاجارين
and he and his family built and lived in a mud hut.
وبنى وعاش هو وعائلته في كوخ من الطين
Years later, the boy from that cramped mud hut
وبعد ذلك بأعوام ، كبر ذلك الولد من كوخ الطين الضيق
would grow up to be the man in that cramped capsule
ليصبح الرجل في تلك الكبسولة الضيقة
on the tip of a rocket
على طرف صاروخ
who volunteered to be launched into outer space,
حيث تطوع ليتم اطلاقه للفضاء الخارجي
the first one of any of us to really physically leave this planet.
أول واحد منا غادر بالفعل هذا الكوكب
And he didn't just leave it,
ولم يغادره فحسب
he circled it once.
لكنه دار حوله مرة .
Fifty years later, as a tribute,
وبعد ذلك بخمسين عاماً ، وكتكريم له
the International Space Station, which is still up there tonight,
قامت محطة الفضاء الدولية والتي لا زالت هناك الليلة
synced its orbit with Gagarin's orbit,
بمحازاة مدارها مع مدار جاجارين
at the exact same time of day,
بالضبط في نفس الوقت من اليوم
and filmed it,
وقامت بتصويره
so you can go online and you can watch over 100 minutes
وبالتالي يمكنك الدخول على الانترنت ومشاهدة أكثر من 100 دقيقة
of what must have been an absolutely mesmerizing ride,
مما يعتبر بحق أكثر الجولات فتنة
possibly a lonely one,
احتمال المرة الوحيدة
the first person to ever see such a thing.
التي يرى فيها شخص مثل هذا الشيئ .
And then when you've had your fill of that,
ومن ثم عندما تشبع من ذلك
you can click on one more link.
يمكنك الضغط على رابط آخر.
You can come back to Earth.
يمكنك العودة إلى الأرض
You return to where you started.
تعود إلى حيث بدأت
You can finish your game.
يمكنك انهاء لعبتك
You just need to find one more fact that you didn't know.
تحتاج فقط للعثور على حقيقة لم تكن تعرفها.
And for me, I quickly landed on this one:
وبالنسبة لي ، فقط هبطت على هذه:
The Earth has a tolerance of about .17 percent from the reference spheroid,
الأرض لديها ما نسبته 0.17 في المائة من التفاوت عن مرجعية الشكل الكروي
which is less than the .22 percent allowed in billiard balls.
والتي تقل عن 0.22 في المائة عن المسموح به في كرات البلياردو.
This is the kind of fact I would have loved as a boy.
هذا النوع من الحقائق الذي قد أعشقه كصبي .
I found it myself.
وجدته بنفسي.
It's got some math that I can do.
وهي تحتوي على بعض الحسابات التي يمكنني اجراءها.
I'm pretty sure my dad doesn't know it.
أنا متأكد تماماً أن أبي لا يعلم هذا .
What this means is that if you could shrink the Earth to the size of a billiard ball,
ما يعنيه هذا هو أنك لو تمكنت من تقليص حجم الأرض إلى حجم كرة البلياردو،
if you could take planet Earth, with all its mountain tops and caves
لو استطعت أخذ كوكب الأرض ، بكل قمم جباله وكهوفه
and rainforests, astronauts and uncontacted tribes and chimpanzees, voodoo dolls,
وغاباته المطيرة ، ورواد فضائه والقبائل المنعزلة والشيمبانزي وعرائس المشعوذين،
fireflies, chocolate, sea creatures making love in the deep blue sea,
اليرعات ، الشوكولاته ، مخلوقات البحر التي تمارس الحب في أعماق البحر الأزرق،
you just shrink that to the size of a billiard ball,
قلصت ذلك إلى حجم كرة البلياردو ،
it would be as smooth as a billiard ball,
ستكون في نعومة كرة البلياردو,
presumably a billiard ball with a slight bulge around the middle.
بافتراض ان كرة البلياردو لها انتفاخ بسيط عند الوسط
That's pretty cool.
هذا جميل بالفعل.
I didn't know that.
لم أكن أعلم ذلك.
Chimborazo!
شيمبرازو!
Thank you.
شكراً .
(Applause)
(تصفيق)